SAMUEL AMPOMAH

nui649@usask.ca | (306) 371-2165 | Saskatoon, SK S7H 0G4

Summary

Economist with over five years of relevant experience in econometric and socio-economic analysis, policy design, and recommendation. A proven track record in economic modeling, environmental and economic impact prediction, and evidence-based policy recommendation. Project management, stakeholder collaboration, and public presentation skills are also demonstrated strengths. An environmental and socio-economic issue analyst focusing on the circular economy, sustainable development, and industrial ecology. Extensive knowledge of environmental legislation, energy systems, and the circular economy principles and willingness to apply knowledge in Alberta economy.

Skills

- Economic and Socio-Economic Analysis
- Environmental Policy Development
- Data Modeling and Forecasting
- Policy development and recommendation
- Project Management and Leadership
- Stakeholder Engagement, Collaboration and Communication
- Research Design and Statistical Analysis
- Project Monitoring and Results Reporting
- Teamwork Collaboration and Public Presentations
- Statistical Methodologies
- Quantitative and qualitative research design and analysis

Education-

University of Saskatchewan | Saskatoon, SK

MSc in Agricultural Economics (09/2022 – 07/2024)

University of Ghana | Accra, Ghana

BSc in Agricultural Economics (08/2017 – 11/2021)

Work Experience

Economic Research Analyst

Department of Agriculture and Resource Economics, University of Saskatchewan | Saskatoon, SK 08/2022 - 07/2024

• Reconstructed the economic impacts of climate change mitigation options for First Nation communities, with a focus on policy development and recommendations.

- Developed policy reports and presented findings to stakeholders, research teams, and government bodies.
- Performed socio-economic analyses, such as benefit-cost analyses and economic impact studies, to inform policy decisions.
- Crafted policy recommendations based on forecast modeling and analysis for Bridge to Land Water Sky for the management of Greenhouse Gas Emission.
- Maintained working relationships with the research team for data collection, complex modeling, and analyses.

Research Analyst

Saskatchewan Intercultural Association (SIA) | Saskatoon, SK

05/2023 - 08/2023

- Designed and implemented research studies evaluating client feedback and service impact.
- Evaluated the validity of research findings and provided recommendations to improve client services.
- Analyzed and interpreted data to identify trends for improvement and adjust policy adjustments.
- Conducted research on collected data sources and analyzed large datasets to identify patterns and trends using economic tools.
- Prepared detailed research findings and communicated results to stakeholders.

Data and Policy Analyst

University of Ghana, Department of Agricultural Economics and Agribusiness | Accra, Ghana

09/2020 - 08/2022

- Formulated policy for the Ghana Economic Growth and International Trade Project, based on a forestry sector study, resulting in steady sector growth since 2021.
- Designed research studies, developed survey tools, and conducted interviews with government organizations and ministries.
- Collected survey data for studies on the economics and policy of sustainable development.
- Analyzed large datasets to inform policy recommendations and development.
- Prepared presentations on policy analysis findings for senior management.
- Prepared and presented comprehensive reports on research findings to academic and governmental audiences.

Volunteering Experience

Community Engagement Project Lead

University of Saskatchewan | Saskatoon, SK

06/2023 - 08/2023

- Designed and implemented client feedback surveys with stakeholders and the Saskatchewan Intercultural Association using Microsoft Forms.
- Collected, cleaned, and analyzed survey data to generate actionable insights and recommendations.
- Organized comprehensive reports and visualizations of survey findings for presentation to stakeholders.
- Collaborated on continuous improvement initiatives, integrating client feedback to enhance services and programs offered by the Saskatchewan Intercultural Association.

Planning and Data Intern

Deutsche Gesellschaft für Internationale Zusammenarbeit (GIZ) Ghana | Accra

04/2018 - 08/2018

- Assisted in collecting, organizing, and analyzing data relevant to various projects, ensuring data accuracy and reliability for informed decision-making.
- Prepared reports and documentation summarizing data findings, project progress, and impact assessments for stakeholders.
- Supported planning and implementation of sustainable development initiatives.
- Coordinated with stakeholders, including local communities and partner organizations, to gather feedback, share updates, and ensure alignment with project goals.

Project Works -

- Economic Analysis of Beneficial Management Practices Adoption for Climate Change on Canola
 Production in Canada: Evidence and Policy Implications from First Nations in Saskatchewan.
- Health Shocks and Rural Farmers Credit Access Shifts in Sub-Saharan Africa: Evidence from the Kwahu Afram Plains South District, Ghana.
- Household Consumption Expenditure Determinants Across Poverty Subgroups in Sub-Sahara Africa:
 Evidence from the Ghanaian Living Standard Survey.

Certifications

Certificate in Ethical Conduct for Research Involving Humans

University of Saskatchewan | Saskatoon, SK (12/2023)

Data Science Certificate

University of Saskatchewan | Saskatoon, SK (06/2023)

References -

Available upon request.